- Hey, folks
and welcome to the lesson
on Responsive Design.
Now, I'm really pumped for this lesson
because if you've watched
this course straight through,
you've probably gotten
something of the idea
that a lot of design is doing
pretty pictures in Figma.
And that is some part of design
but really the point
of design is to create
beautiful, usable websites
that go into the real world
and millions of people benefit from them.
And one of the key skills
in bridging the gap
between pretty pictures in Figma
and great websites in the real
world is responsive design.
Responsive design if you
haven't heard the term
is best thought of as
device agnostic design.
It refers to the idea that
whether I ask for a website
from my tiny little phone
or my medium size tablet
or my larger desktop or laptop
or extra large monitor
on, attached to a desktop,
whatever screen size I'm using,
whatever capabilities of that device,
the website looks and
works as good as possible
given where it's being requested from.
It responds to the
device that requests it.
So in this lesson, as always,
we are going to be doing a live example
that sort of shows over my shoulder
as I think about the real world concerns
of responsive design
but we're also going to be looking at
a ton of great examples
from around the web,
and that's where we're
gonna be starting now.
Let's get started.
So perhaps the biggest first question
with responsive design
is what exactly responds?
What exactly changes
across different devices?
And I'll just say, 90% of the time
you're thinking about
responsive design, if not more,
you're going to be thinking
about changes in screen width.
Like there are other things
that change about a website
and we'll look at them
but the most important
and the one that causes
the most issues, and the most
thought, and the most work
is going to be dealing with
different device widths.
You might think that
screen height would also be
something that's like an
important change across devices
but it's largely irrelevant,
and the main reason for that
is we're already used to
sites having vertical scrolling.
So whatever the height of this content is,
it almost doesn't matter
because I'm just gonna know
I have to scroll down until
I get to the bottom anyways.
But the width does matter
because if all of this
content just runs off the side
and I have to horizontally
scroll back and forth to see it,
that's considered much
more of an inconvenience
and something that I
don't normally have to do.
So, while I will often
shrink a website's width down
to see how it appears on mobile,
I'll almost never adjust the height
simply because it doesn't make
that much of a difference.
Like maybe if there was a
bunch of fixed UI at the bottom
or the top or something like that,
then you'd wanna make sure
that a very short phone
could still see stuff.
But again, by and large,
we are focusing on screen width here.
Now another important
change across devices
is whether you have
your finger to tap stuff
on a glass screen,
or you have a mouse cursor
flying around the screen.
And that matters in a few different ways.
One of them is hover states.
So certainly if I load up
Dribbble.com on my phone,
it's not gonna work exactly
the same way that it's working right now.
You'll notice when I hover
over this following dropdown,
it like has a little highlight.
Let's see, same thing with filters
the border gets slightly darker.
And there's things that start to appear
when I hover over an individual shot.
All of these things can
more or less work the same.
Sometimes web browsers
on phones will recognize
that something should be a hover state.
And so when you tap something once
you'll actually see the hover state.
But there is a certain
type of hover interaction
that won't work on the phone
and this is something you're going to want
to make sure you avoid.
That's anything where you have to hover
on a parent element and
then keep hovering on it
in order to access something
like a child element.
So Gmail kinda famously does this.
It's a great interaction on desktop
but it's absolutely
impossible on a mobile device
and you should make sure
that in the world of responsive
design, you're avoiding it.
Another place where it matters
whether you have a touch device
or a device with a mouse
cursor is the size of targets.
So this is like whatever you're
clicking on or tapping on.
And when I have a mouse
cursor on my screen there,
it comes to a one pixel point
in kinda the upper left
hand side of that cursor,
that arrow.
And I can see exactly what it is
that I'm going to click
on at any given point.
It's like pretty easy to establish that.
But if I'm on a phone screen,
I'm basically sticking my finger here
and like, consider that you can't even see
the part of your finger
that taps the phone first.
It's all kind of obscured
by the rest of your finger.
So it makes it sort of a clunky
means of interacting with a screen
compared to something like a cursor.
It's for this reason that you've
heard me say in the course
and I will say it again,
that on mobile, tap targets
should typically be much bigger
and on iPhone, they give the guidelines
of 44 pixels by 44 pixels.
And on Android, they give
the guidance of 48 by 48.
So you don't need to do
this 100% of the time,
in a lot of like text links
it may be very difficult to do this,
but the size of the area
that will lead you to
some destination or some
action should be 44 by 44
as often as possible on mobile.
So all these details
of the responsive design work you're doing
need to be captured in a responsive plan
and maybe this is an overly
constrained way of saying it.
I'm not saying that you need
to have something on paper,
although you almost certainly would have
some texts somewhere.
Like at the minimum you need
to sit down with your developer
and open up Figma and go over
exactly what's gonna happen
in a number of situations.
Your responsive plan should
cover three things primarily.
The first is where does space
get added and subtracted?
And by this, I just mean
if I have this design,
and this is app,
let's say I'm doing Shift
+ Command, Control + 4
which is the Mac shortcut for
taking a little screenshot
but I use it as a handy
way to measure width.
So this is 500 pixels wide.
If I have a design that's 500 pixels wide
and someone views it on a device
that's like 510 pixels wide,
where does the extra space get added?
Like you can see it gets added
into this margin and this margin, right?
'Cause the Dribbble logo
doesn't get any bigger,
these icons don't get any wider.
But what does get wider
is this shot, right?
So it doesn't get added
to the margins here,
it gets added to the content.
And all these little details of like
where does the next 10 pixels of space go?
Or if the screen is shrinking,
where does that space get taken from?
All of those details need
to be in a responsive plan.
Another important thing
for a responsive plan
is where do break points occur?
A break point is the fancy industry term
for like a major layout change.
So again, going back to
our Dribbble example,
as the screen gets bigger,
everything here is like
a very local change.
I'm just adding little space
into margins or content.
And then at some point, boop,
we hit this point where things snap.
And let's say, you know,
this is at a width of
620 pixels, roughly.
So if I'm the designer for Dribbble
I'm gonna make a responsive plan
and I'm going to say
in some form or another
around 620 pixels we
should snap from having a
single column of shots to two columns.
And that's not the only
sort of break point
I wanna think about.
In fact that one could be specified
just by talking about grid behavior.
There's gonna be other
things that are like totally
like sort of separate styling changes.
So as I continue to make
the screen wider and wider,
a perfect example is we saw the header
go from this sort of mobile version
where I've got a hamburger menu
and a couple icons and a logo to a,
I think this is the
full on desktop version.
Yeah, so there's, look at this actually,
there's a couple different
versions you can see here.
So I have this medium version
where I have all of this content displayed
and then there's a tight spacing
between these little items right here.
And then as I get even bigger,
that spacing increases.
So maybe that's at 1200 pixels or so
the spacing gets even bigger.
And so, that's just for the header
but you can see there's
also margin changes
going on in the body here.
And so all of these things
happen at separate break points.
And your responsive documentation
is going to wanna cover
both things, right?
When there's a small change,
where does the space get
added to or taken away from?
And then when there's a big change,
what does the shift look like before
and what does it look like after?
One thing I like to do
and you'll see this later on the video
is just to make sure that when
I have like a break point,
I wanna see what the layout looks like
at the widest version of one,
as well as the narrowest
version of the next.
And then if there's more,
I'm gonna go to the widest
version of that next one.
And just to make sure that
basically at every size,
things look as intuitive and logical
and sensible as possible.
And the goal is just to make
sure that every possible size
the design looks just like
it was completely designed
100% for that size.
Now, what I consider sort
of the full range of sizes
for most projects is
going from something like
about 300 pixels wide,
which the smallest iPhone is 320 pixels.
And so that's, I think
a fairly good minimum,
unless you need to design something
for like a smartwatch browser.
But you'll notice that
Chrome-based browsers such as Brave
can't actually shrink to
320 pixels very easily,
unless you open up the dev tools.
So that's Option + Command I.
And if I just do this,
there's a couple ways
of then seeing what's going on here.
So the dev tools.
I can use this little three dot menu
to make sure they're
docked on the right side.
And then once they're
docked on the right side,
I now can go smaller than 500 pixels.
And what's more, it lets me know
the size that I'm looking at.
So I can like go to 320 here
and make sure the design looks good.
I can also press this little
device button right here
which is just going to
have some common devices
such as, again, the smallest
iPhone size that I can load up
and see how things will appear.
On the opposite end of the spectrum,
I think of looking at the device,
certainly at 2000 to 3000 pixels as being
kind of the widest that
anyone might want to.
Layouts don't typically change
beyond about this screen size right here.
So this is 1440.
And if I wanted to see what
this site would look like
or at least some approximation
of it on a very large screen,
what I'm gonna do is just
press Command + Minus
which shrinks the screen.
So if I shrink it, for
instance down to 50%,
it's essentially taking
the version of this website
that's for double 1440, so 2800 pixels,
and displaying what I'd see there.
So if I had a monitor that
was almost 3000 pixels wide,
I would see one, two, three, four, five
six, seven different shots across
the homepage of dribbble.com.
And that's just a quick way to say,
okay, how is this site gonna
look granted it zoomed out,
but how would this look
on an even larger monitor?
So shrink down like this or with dev tools
and use Command + Minus
to see what it would look
like on a larger screen.
And then the final thing
in your responsive plan
should be what states apply
only to certain screen sizes?
So for instance, if I
go down to a very small
version of the Dribbble site,
I can bring up in this menu
but there's really no way
to have a menu like this
on a desktop size screen.
It really only applies to a mobile screen.
So I just wanna be careful
that that's noted somehow
that there's going to be a
mobile design for this menu here
and it's not gonna have an analog
for any other screen size.
And typically that's how it goes.
Mobile has more, maybe
it has a search state
or a menu state or a pop over or something
that just isn't present
in any other screen size.
You just wanna make sure
you're capturing all those.
Now I wanna talk about a couple just
overall good principles to keep in mind
while you're doing responsive design.
I promise we're gonna get to the
live demo in Figma real soon
but these are just things
that you're gonna want to keep in mind
across all responsive
design work that you do.
The first is that the break points
should be determined by the content.
So, all that means is ideally
when you are creating a
responsive design for a website
things shouldn't really change layout
until the content determines
that they need to.
And so, for instance,
when I look at this header right here,
just like ignore the
whole rest of the screen.
But when I look at this header,
it's not until the search bar
gets kind of awkwardly
close to Hire Designers
until there's like a
little layout snap, right?
As long as there's enough
space where it's clear
that Search and Hire
Designers are totally distinct
and the stuff has kind
of the right content
and the stuff is the left content,
as long as there's enough
space for that to be clear,
then it's one layout.
But as soon as they start
getting awkwardly close,
the layout snaps.
And I don't know exactly
what width that's at,
we could find out fairly easily here
but the whole idea is we want
this, it's at 1200 let's say.
We want this to be based
on the actual screen size
and kind of what the content wants,
the alternative being, say designing
just for a few specific sizes.
So this is something I've
been guilty of it in the past
but like for instance,
you'll see a lot of sites
where they might have a break point
at very common device
sizes like 568, 375, 1024.
And a lot of those,
like 1024 is a very
common iPad screen size.
And so if you see a break point for that,
like oftentimes they're just
trying to make sure that
at that width everything
looks really good,
but you might go to 1023
and find that things look much funkier.
And that is not the right idea.
You want every screen size to
look perfectly designed for
as native for one screen
size as for another.
To those ends what you
wanna do is translate
your website conceptually, not literally.
So, that's a bit of an odd thing to say
but what I mean by that can be sort of
viewed on this example here.
So this is Contents Magazine
and just pay attention to
let's say like the header
and this background image
because in this area alone,
as I shrink the screen size down,
you're gonna notice what happens is
it's not just like the book
images, let's take those first.
It's not just like the book
images get scaled down.
They're kinda shifting around
and then they snap down.
And I don't even know if
this is the same image here.
And then as I continue to go farther,
they start to interfere with the content
so then they just peek out from over here.
Like this is a very different layout
in some sense than the
wider widths, right?
And then here we go, we
have another big change
kind of for our mobile header.
And in some sense, this
feels like very different,
almost like a different design
and yeah, okay, fair enough,
it kind of is a different design.
The point here though is they
took like the overall feel
of what they're trying to convey.
Like, oh, there should
be these colorful books
and they kinda have this textured pattern
and they're scattered about.
And at the widest width we
want them to be scattered
in a way that's natural for the content
that's displayed here
which I would say they were successful at.
But then as the screen size shrinks,
what's gonna look more natural here
for the books to be scattered about,
something more like this.
You couldn't just use this amount of books
on a smaller screen.
And they keep the same thing
all the way down to mobile
where it's just like
a little smattering of
books at the very top.
And obviously you have
narrower side margins
and so they don't even
include them down there.
So they've taken the concept
and they've translated that.
They haven't literally
taken say the same design
and scaled it or tried to do
anything kinda basic like that.
Likewise, the header is
also a good example of this.
They said, okay, what does
our header need to convey
on a mobile device?
We've got the logo.
Sure, that's important.
And then maybe an Explore
which if you click this
it's actually gonna bring you down
to the bottom of the page
and you can see all the
stuff that's in the header,
all those sort of nav items.
And when it's expanded,
yes, you can see them all
including the search box.
But if you're on a mobile device,
it's not as important
relative to the content
so we're gonna hide it.
We're gonna relegate it
behind this button click.
And the idea of a header is still there
but we've just changed the content.
So they've done a good
job of doing this sort of
conceptual translation.
What is the role of a
header on a mobile device?
What should it include on a mobile device
versus what can it include
on a desktop screen?
What they did not try to do
was cram all of this
stuff on a smaller screen
and have the like most
important content here
get pushed down hundreds of pixels lower.
The third tenet of good responsive
design that I wanna cover
is often called mobile first
although in my book, it's more
important to generalize this
to what I call hardest first.
But I'm sure many of you have
heard the term mobile first
so let me just take a
minute and talk about that.
Mobile first refers to
designing for a small screen
before designing for a large screen.
And why would you do this?
Because it forces absolute
clarity on what's important.
When you have a smaller
screen size to work with,
you're forced to say, look,
the content is what's
really important here.
So even the nav items in the header,
we're going to minimize those
and hide them behind the click
and you're gonna have to jump
down the page to see them.
That's sort of a hard decision to make.
But when you're faced with
very little screen real estate,
you have to make those hard decisions.
You have to say this is what's critical
to show up high right away.
Someone doesn't need to scroll to see it
and they don't need to click to see it.
But if you solve that tough problem
of prioritizing the content
when space is at a minimum,
it makes it just downright
easy to make a larger version.
And the inverse is if
you do the large version
but you're kind of undisciplined
about what you put on the screen,
trying to make a small version
can be a lot more work,
both for the designer and the developer,
since you weren't really
clear about what was important
and you may not have designed or developed
in such a way that makes
it easy to scale down.
I'm also just gonna add a personal note
that following this
process of mobile first
helps a lot with client work too.
Because if you have a client
and your first conversations are like,
what are the absolute most critical things
to show on the smallest
version of this website?
They don't get to say
everything's important.
Like they have to do
the hard work with you
and you get to figure out
what truly is critical.
And then again, when you
expand to a larger screen,
it just makes it all that much
easier to fit the things in.
Now, like I allude to here though,
mobile first is not the end
of the story in my book.
I think mobile first works great
when you have a lot of
content on the page,
a lot of elements, a lot of interactions.
When you just have a
really complicated page,
designing mobile first is fantastic.
But what I found in my own experience
is that when you don't have
quite so much content on the page
and say, you have like a landing page,
a marketing page of some sort,
if I have that, then I might
wanna design desktop first,
get it looking really,
really nice on sort of,
on this wide canvas, so to speak.
And then when the canvas shrinks down,
like I can shrink down the visuals here
but there's no guarantee
that if I'm trying to make
something that's just
like really stunning.
But what I found is if I'm
trying to make a website
just look really stunning,
mobile screens are kind of
a small canvas to work with
and oftentimes you wanna figure out
like the overall effect on a larger kinda,
on a larger canvas like a desktop screen.
So maybe a good way to think about this
is design whatever is hardest first.
If the interaction is the
hard part, go with mobile
because interactions are harder to design
on a smaller screen.
But if the visuals are kinda the hard part
then perhaps design desktop first
because it's harder to
get it right on desktop
but then you can scale it down.
With all that out of the way,
I wanna talk about some
of the general patterns
that you will use in
designing responsive websites.
The first one is what
I call rows-to-columns
and microsoft.com is a website
that exemplifies this pattern very nicely.
So if I look for like a row of content,
so for instance like this right here,
you'll notice that one
thing that happens is
on a mobile layout,
this row as soon as
there's not room for it
actually becomes a column.
And sure, like the images
are now on the left
and the text is now on the right
rather than the text being
below the different icons here.
But like there's overall this shift where
when the screen gets narrower,
things that were laid out in a row
have to now be laid out in a column.
So we're gonna see the same thing
with this content right here.
Now it's a little bit
of a grid, interesting,
but then I go down even farther
and it just becomes an all-out column.
And so this is true for
things that are like
more obviously rows
but then even when things
are sort of rows only
at a conceptual level,
this strategy still works.
So for instance, when I look
at this image right here,
what I see is there's like the
text and button on one side
and then on the other side,
there's sort of this image
with these controllers.
And even if the image was kind
of all across this rectangle,
this is still like the
focal point to the image.
So in a sense, this is
a row with two items,
some text and a focal point of an image.
And so, when that screen shrinks down,
we're gonna scroll down to see it here.
Things change.
What was a row is now a column,
the focal point of the images at the top
and the text with the
button's at the bottom.
So et cetera.
You can like look at all of...
You can look at all kinds of sites
and see tons of examples of this, right?
Even right down to the footer
here I have a row of columns.
And when I shrink down, that becomes,
surprise, a column of columns.
So you get the idea here.
Take what starts as rows on large screens
and make them columns on smaller screens.
Another pattern that is very important
and seen all the time is to hide content.
So this is the new site, FiveThirtyEight,
we're gonna be looking at
a bunch of different examples here.
But you'll notice when I shrink
from a desktop version of this
site to a smaller version,
at some point, all of these
menu items get hidden, right?
They're hidden behind this
little button that says Menu.
And when I click Menu,
I can see my nice little menu right there.
I can close it and so on.
The whole idea of the hide pattern is
you don't need to show
everything by default,
you can hide it behind a
click or in this case, a tap.
And that's what I mean.
We're not hiding it
where users can find it,
we're hiding it behind a single click.
And when they make a click,
then they can see those options
that are maybe a little secondary
to the main content on the page.
Another pattern that is super important
in responsive design is drop
and drop just refers to placing something
further down the page.
So for instance, you'll
see there's in general,
three columns here.
Got the main column, the content,
then there's The Latest, and
then there's interactives.
And when I kinda shrink this screen
such that three columns can no longer fit,
those other columns didn't get removed,
they got dropped, right?
So there's more stories,
interactives I think
is one of the columns.
By the way, this is,
I mean on very nicely designed site
but right now when I'm scrolling through,
I don't get the sense that
FiveThirtyEight was designed
for this width in particular.
There's just way too much space,
not enough content, it's kinda awkward.
This is something where
as nice as this site is,
if they had a more solid responsive plan,
this would look like perfectly native
and perfectly well-designed
even as sort of these
awkward screen widths.
And really the place
where you will see these,
where it's kinda hardest to do
is that space between kind
of wide mobile devices
and sort of portrait tablets.
Oftentimes it's too
small to have a sidebar
so you're not gonna have
side by side columns
but it's wide enough that it can just look
a little bit awkward to try
and apply a mobile layout here.
And then the final general pattern
I wanna talk about is remove.
So this is where on a smaller screen,
the content that appears on
larger screens just disappears
and it's not accessible behind the click,
it's not just dropped to
the bottom of the page,
it's just gone.
So for instance, one place we see this
is with updating the latest polls
and I shrink this on down.
And if I shrink this
page to a mobile size,
I do not see that text anywhere.
There's just no way to access it.
So maybe that seems like
kind of a trivial example
but we'll look at a whole bunch more.
Just a couple other examples real quick.
So this is Opal C1,
a webcam that's supposed
to be very high quality.
And if I shrink this page on down,
you'll notice a lot of this header content
like the product name and
the colors and the price
are just totally gone.
And it's interesting 'cause it's not like
they're totally unimportant
pieces of information
but they don't necessarily
need to be in the header
the entire time that
you're scrolling on mobile.
So that's why Opal made the
decision to remove that stuff.
It is worth noting though
that in the process of buying,
you will see color and
price before you reserve.
So while this was removed from the header,
it's not like the price
is totally inaccessible
if you're on a mobile device.
Stripe is another
interesting example here.
So I've got these like sample
devices off to the right here.
And then as I shrink my screen down,
well, I can just go ahead and do it,
you'll notice the devices are just gone.
Like there is no mobile version of them.
There could be but in this
case they said, you know what?
They're not really adding anything
until we're kind of at this awkward width.
And so before we get to that width,
we will just have them be totally removed.
Might also be worth noting
that two of these patterns,
hide and remove,
are also some of the six
strategies of simplicity.
So if you wanna review more
examples of this stuff,
go watch the Simplicity lesson.
Now I'm gonna be talking about
a lot more responsive patterns
but at this point, let's start
breaking open this example,
and we'll talk about other
responsive design patterns
in the context of an actual example.
So I'll go through and make
a bunch of different designs
at various screen sizes
in a very realistic way
for what I would do
and what I'd wanna pass on to a developer
if I was working on this site.
So our sample app today, Rebalancr,
is just this site that tracks
your savings for retirement
or for a new house or whatever,
and you're able to automatically
keep a portfolio balanced
across things like say stocks and bonds
and just various index funds.
So this would be something
that I think would be
pretty cool if it existed
and so I just designed
up this quick mock-up.
When I go to make it work
at other screen sizes,
pretty much the first
thing I'm gonna look at
is I'm just gonna start at the top.
I'm gonna think about this
navigation right here.
And so, one decent thing to do
just to get the screen
sizes working a little bit
is to take all these
items that are in the nav
and make a frame out of them.
So I'm gonna do Option +
Command + G and you see.
So you can see their frame seven now
but we can just call this Nav.
And now I just need to set
a little resizing behavior
for these elements so that
they work appropriately.
Right now when I resize the
frame, nothing much happens.
And instead, what I want to
have happen is for instance,
this to float in the center,
this stuff to stay fixed to
the right hand side here,
and this background,
let me just make sure
I have the background.
To grab this background
and this should be fixed to the left,
right, top, and bottom
of its parent element.
So now as a resize, perfect.
I get something that's like
a little bit more sane here.
I guess technically I could
have all three of these things
be fixed to the center vertically as well.
Not that I really anticipate any sizes,
size changes like this.
But the important thing here
is now I'm answering the question of,
if things get 10 pixels
smaller or 10 pixels bigger,
where does that space go?
So we're gonna play around
with this in isolation.
I've got this version
that's 1152 right now.
I'm gonna start shrinking it down
until I feel like it's getting awkward.
And I think the first thing
that's getting awkward here
is when research comes
too close to search.
And so at that point, it's sort of,
like this is all content
that's right-aligned
and this content is centered
and I want that to be clear.
So maybe at about a thousand pixels,
that actually seems like
a good break point here.
I'll say the layout is actually
going to snap a little bit
and instead this will
be the smallest version
of this layout
and we'll go with one
that's even smaller here,
so do 999 pixels.
But what we'll do is we'll
actually minimize this search bar
so that it's effectively,
the rest of the search bar
is hidden behind the click.
So I can drag the search
icon into that auto layout
and close this or delete that.
And so here's what the new
layout would look like.
And this is fine but now
I'm in the state where
I actually have another state
that I'm now gonna see if
my screen size is 999 pixels
which is what is the
expanded search state?
So I'm gonna make a
quick mock-up of that too
and I'm kinda gonna have
them be grouped a little bit.
Here we go.
So this is one break point, right?
I've got the smallest
version of it at 1000
another version at 1152.
Then I have another break point here,
this is 999 so the biggest version of it,
plus I've got the search open here.
And then I wanna explore and kinda see
what is the smallest possible
version of this break point?
In order to figure that out,
I'm basically going to be saying,
when does this content get
to close to right here?
So I can just kinda shrink
this screen size down.
And certainly, I mean, at 700,
I don't even think, yeah,
700's gonna collide.
So I would say something like 800 pixels
is gonna be the max size
for this break point.
And if I really wanted to,
I could do a minimized version of that too
but I don't really feel like I need to.
And then we're gonna
have another break point
where things become even more collapsed.
So maybe what we'll do
here is we'll just say
when the search is actually open,
instead of potentially
running into this logo,
it actually just takes
over the entire nav bar
and there's sort of a state for searching.
So I'm gonna ungroup this
stuff, remove these things.
And we'll put this here.
Now I'm gonna have this be fixed
to the left and to the right.
And actually shoot, this is a group.
I don't actually want this to be a group
because in Figma when I resize groups
just have really wonky behavior.
Oftentimes if something needs
to resize intelligently,
it needs to be a frame instead of a group.
So I'll make this a frame
and then we'll fix it to
the left and right side
and then this will just be
fixed to the right side.
That should be enough for
this to work intelligently.
It looks like what I need to do
is just say this should be on
the left and so should this.
There we go.
All right, that's gonna work perfectly.
So now I've got this new break point
that functions in this way
and I'm gonna explore what
is the smallest possible
state that this can have
I would say about 500 pixels,
this search bar is starting
to get so close to here
that this space is not clearly bigger
than this space, right?
That's if you remember the spacing lesson,
the law of inner and outer spacing.
I always want the space
around a group of items
to be more than the space
between the items in that group.
So at 500, below 500,
I'm gonna jump to a totally
new type of layout here.
And actually I think at this point,
what I'm gonna do is go with something
like a hamburger menu.
It's just super popular
and there's a reason why,
so maybe I'll do something
like center this.
I'll have a hamburger menu
but it'll be on the right hand side.
Sorry, the left hand
side as is most typical.
Center that.
They use 16 pixel margins
which is pretty standard for mobile.
And then with this Deposit button,
maybe I'll even remove the word Deposit
and just have the button here.
Now I need the button to be square
and I also need the button
to have an appropriate
tap target size, 44 by 44.
I can't control these numbers directly
since this is an auto layout
so it's its own frame,
but I can with these margins.
So if I just do something
like 12 all around,
that's 35 by 35.
So there we go.
If I do 16, that's 43 by 43.
That I'm gonna call good enough.
And probably default it
towards being at the top there.
And yeah, that looks like
it's gonna work great.
So I wanna make sure that is centered
and fixed on the right hand side.
This is fixed on the left-hand side
and our logo is centered in the middle.
But at this point, now I know
I have even more work to do
which is I now have another
state that only occurs
when I'm at this break point.
I need to show what this
looks like when this is open.
So, let's duplicate this.
I'm gonna bring it on down to
again, kinda the most
small reasonable size
that I like to think about, 320.
Goodness.
There we go, 320. Perfect.
And I'm actually gonna use
AIF to create a new frame
and just create like a phone's,
actually why even bother
doing this by hand?
iPhone SE 320 by 568.
And we'll just drag this nav onto here.
And I'm gonna show what
this menu looks like
when it's opened.
So first of all, when the menu is open
the menu should have a way to close it.
And what's typical is you
see the hamburger button
turn into an X and then maybe I will also,
I'll actually ungroup
all this stuff for now
but I'll take this and say
this'll just kinda fly down.
And maybe the background
color is a little bit darker.
So I can sort of see this menu here.
And then what items will I need there?
I will certainly need
research and advisors,
so I'll go ahead and put those.
Actually we'll do it all in one text box.
Research and advisers.
but then because I'm making this menu,
I'm kind of prone to say,
what else might go in this menu?
Like if I'm on a mobile device,
I'm not gonna have this
sidebar right here.
So, I'm also thinking I should
take some of these elements
and put them into that sidebar
or sorry, that mobile menu as well.
So I'll just bring this
stuff right down here.
Actually, what we can do is
just slide all this here.
I'm gonna remove the
highlight on Retirement.
With this Add Portfolio
if I didn't want the plus
maybe I'd do something like italicize it.
Doesn't super, super matter.
And then I need some title
for research and advisors.
Like I'm gonna put other
maybe which is pretty awful
but it works for now.
Now this text right here,
all of this text, like
each item, each line
should be its own tap target.
Which means the total height of the line
which is the line height
plus the paragraph spacing
should be 44 at a minimum.
So if I set these all at 24,
like that's one way to do it
but now they just look really spread out.
So one thing I like to do on mobile
is just make this text a
heck of a lot bigger too.
So if I do that here,
there's still 10 pixels
of space between that.
Maybe I'll move this down
so it's more like say 32 pixels of space.
I'll grab the same thing.
There we go. 32 pixels of space.
I will need to make this
background a little bit bigger.
And if I put these in groups,
I can play around with this fairly simply.
Yeah, maybe something like this.
So as a mobile menu this
seems to perform very nicely.
Like it looks good.
And there we go, for a mobile menu,
I think this works really nicely.
We've got these nice big tap targets.
It still has a nice look to it.
I'd wanna view it on
an actual mobile device
as always to make sure it looks good
but I have done that and
it does, can confirm.
So at this point, I think
I'm ready to move on a bit.
Now before we go on,
I wanna talk about some
other navigation patterns
that you'll see.
We did something here where
we sort of hid the menu
behind buttons and that's,
I mean, fairly common.
If I just like slide on over to Stripe,
got the same exact thing going on
but the hamburger menu is
on the right-hand side.
And then see all this
stuff and I can click here
and it closes.
Another navigation pattern
that's sort of similar
but also good to know
about and be thinking about
is an off-canvas effect.
So here I have on the World
Wildlife Foundation website
what looks like sort of the
same hamburger menu right here.
When I click it though,
what's interesting is the menu
slides in and it slides over.
So it sort of has this
like physicality to it
where it's supposed to be
kind of in the real world.
It's like one piece of
material over another
and the one in the background
then becomes darker.
But this is nice because it gives you
a sort of a sense of place
and where possible, it's
great to add these animations
so that it doesn't just sort of snap
from one version of
the screen, to the next
which can be kinda confusing.
But instead the user
can see what's happening
in between the different states.
If you have a lot of items
that you need to show in navigation,
one interesting mobile
effect is prioritized items.
And so this just refers to schemes
where you're taking, let's
say, a list like this.
We have Fundamentals, Tools,
Updates, and Case Studies.
And you'll notice that as
the screen gets smaller,
there's a More.
There wasn't a More before
but there's a More now.
And right now, this More
only includes Case Studies.
And if the screen gets smaller still,
this More includes
Updates and Case Studies.
And if the screen gets smaller still,
I bet you can tell where this is going.
Tools, Updates, and Case
Studies are all here
until let's see, does
everything just become a More?
No, we go to this
and hey, we have a nice
little slide over effect.
Amazon web services does
something that's somewhat similar.
So I've got a lot of
different items in this nav
but you'll notice that as I go to a width
where they're not all visible,
I can still use this little arrow button
to scroll through them.
So if I click on this arrow button,
it goes to the first one
that's not fully visible,
in this case, AWS Marketplace
and that becomes what's
all the way on the left.
But I can see 'cause of this fade out here
that there's more to the left
if I were to click this arrow.
So these two ways are just possibilities
for how you can kind
of prioritize content.
By the way, if you didn't catch
that right at the very end,
everything goes to a
hamburger menu anyways.
And so, it's not like you
need to use just one of these,
instead you can kind of mix and match
across various screen widths.
Another good and easy navigation
pattern to think about
is doing a footer anchor.
So, this is something that we saw
with the Contents Magazine page.
All that's happening is
if the screen gets to be
a small enough width
and I click here to see the nav,
it's actually bringing me to the nav
at the bottom of the page.
I'm not on a different page.
I'm just at, in HTML
terminology, an anchor element
that leads me to the
bottom of the page, a link.
In my own site I do something
that's a little bit different,
I call it a stacked navigation
and you'll see variations of this.
But it's kind of,
in some sense, it's like a riff
on the rows to column pattern.
So as this screen gets
smaller and smaller,
at some point, there's not enough room
to show all this in the navigation
so I snapped to having two
columns of nav rather than one.
And I like this a lot
because this navigation looks
very natural at this width
and it looks very natural at this width.
And there's really no
at which the navigation
doesn't seem natural.
But one room for improvement is right now,
these little articles are
like kind of awkwardly wide
so, there's always trade offs
and there's always room for improvement.
The goal with responsive design as always
is that at every single width
things look as native and
intuitive as possible.
Back in Figma I should just mention
that I had one oversight on this page
which is I didn't put the search here.
What I would definitely want to do
is make sure that search
was present on this menu
and the place where I'd probably put it
is toward the top right here,
maybe kind of in this general area.
And then it's going to push
all of this other content down.
But what's more is because
of tap target sizes,
I'm going to want this to
be more than 34 pixels,
it doesn't have to be quite 44
but it's not a bad idea.
If it doesn't look incredibly
awkward and chunky,
I'm gonna try and
default to being as close
to that tap target size as possible.
All right.
So now I've made a bunch of
responsive versions of this nav
but if you think about it,
my job is not necessarily done.
I've gotten successively smaller
based on the starting width
but I never bothered to
say what should happen
if this nav becomes really, really big.
And like one option is it
just stays the same scheme.
This stays centered,
this stays on the left,
this stays on the right.
That's totally possible.
But another thing you'll
see very frequently
is what I call a max
width container pattern.
And so, let me just kind of
demo both of these possibilities
because technically we're
gonna look at three,
but there's really two
that are the most common.
So, I'm gonna take this content
and just kind of group
the sidebar as one thing
and group the main content as one thing.
And right now the scheme is
this content has about 48 pixels
between the sidebar and the content
and then 44 pixels on the right-hand side.
And as it is, that's sort of underdefined.
If I start making the
screen 10 pixels bigger,
it's not clear where
those 10 pixels will go.
I could do something for instance
where the content floats
evenly between the sidebar
which is always locked on the left
and the right-hand side of
the screen, so there we go.
Could just kind of center that
and then I'll keep this
locked to the left.
And let's see, will this work?
Yes, it will.
So then even if I have a very wide screen,
we could do something like 2000 pixels,
all of this content would
maintain a logical layout
throughout all those screen widths.
Now this is only one way to do it
and sometimes you'll look at a design
and you'll see, for instance, a logo
way off to the left here
or all this stuff way off to the right.
There'll be nothing else even close to it.
And you say, no, that's kinda awkward,
I don't wanna do that.
And so when that's the case,
another pattern that I think works better
is to take, say all of the content here.
So now I've taken all of this content
and what I've done is sort
of made it stay centered
within this sort of invisible
container right here.
Here's the left edge of
that invisible container
and here's the right edge.
And so even as the screen
gets bigger and bigger,
the invisible container
never gets any bigger.
Now these are the two main ways
of sort of thinking about containers.
Either they have a max width
or they're infinite width,
they just kind of go on forever.
And these honestly,
if you just bounce back and forth
and think of which of
these is the most logical
in various circumstances,
like these are the two main patterns
for containers that you'll see.
In this case, I don't actually think
it's the end of the world
that this sidebar and stuff is so far away
because there's a well-known
UX principle called Fitt's law
which says that the time it
takes to move your mouse cursor
from one place to another
is dramatically shorter
if that destination is
on the edge of the screen
or the corner.
'Cause I can just sort of
slam my mouse into the corner
and it doesn't matter that it's like
thousands of pixels away,
it's still gonna be
pretty easy to get to this
deposit button or one of these other items
on this nav right here.
That being said,
maybe this looks a little
less awkward overall.
And so I could go with something like this
but other others might find
that this like huge amount
of space on either side
just sort of seems like a waste
or seems a little bit more awkward.
And so, I think there is like a little bit
of personal preference
to a decision like this.
We've looked at container patterns
just in the context of
a little app like that
but there's all sorts of
places where you'll see them.
Infinite-width containers are really
the main pattern that you'll see
whenever there's something
with the background.
So, for instance, if I just kind of like
zoom out a bunch here,
this black header is in a sense
an infinite-width container
'cause there's this
black background color,
there is an element in HTML
that stretches all the
way from the left side
to the right side.
Likewise images like this,
like big splash images,
those are very often gonna be
infinite-width containers as well.
And in responsive design,
keeping an image looking good
even when this container can
kind of get wider and wider
is definitely a difficulty at times.
But then if we think about
that other container pattern,
the max-width pattern,
that's something we see plenty here
'cause there's definitely
a max-width going on
kind of from this edge to here.
And it looks like this
text is very likely,
this headline is centered
within that container
and then either that container
or a very similar one
is used just below with
this content as well.
Now this grid stuff is kind of interesting
because this is actually an example
of the third container pattern
which I call a snap-width container.
A snap-width container is a
little bit like a max-width
but, let me just zoom in to 100% here.
That max-width changes.
So right now this grid,
the whole grid has the same width.
But as soon as I get down to
a width that makes it awkward,
it snaps to a smaller size.
And then the same pattern repeats itself
and as soon as it gets down to this size,
boop, it just snaps
down to a smaller size.
So in this case, almost
entirely a single column
and let's see, same thing
happens one more time.
So doing something like
this really works out nicely
because overall, if I
have all these grid items
and these various layouts that
these grid items could take,
I only have to verify that they work
when the grid is like, say this size,
this size, this size, and this size.
And then does it get any bigger from here?
Nope. It doesn't get
any bigger after that.
Like so many of these responsive patterns,
the container patterns are also ones
that you can kind of mix and match.
So with this MDCalc
design that I worked on,
if I go and I search
some result right here,
if I'm on the mobile view
these results appear to be infinite width.
They appear like they're gonna take up
the full screen width no matter what.
But I get a little bit bigger
and then all of a sudden
they're not infinite-width
but they are expanding into this container
that does appear to be infinite-width
until we find the max-width
for that container.
And then it snaps to something even bigger
and that's it, there's no
more snapping after that.
But the idea is I can
sort of switch between
whether the container patterns
are expanding without bound,
expanding with bound,
or snapping from one width to another.
And I can do whatever is
necessary to keep the layout
as aligned as possible at
all different screen widths
and looking as natural
and intuitive as possible
at all different screen widths.
Now, if I'm thinking about
going through this app
kinda from top to bottom
and just making everything responsive,
the next big thing I'm gonna wonder about
is this sidebar right here.
And as far as sidebar patterns go,
there's really only a few
that we ever think about.
One is to drop the sidebar.
And we already talked about dropping
as being one of the fundamental patterns
of responsive design.
Dropping the sidebar just means
putting it lower down in the screen.
So in the FiveThirtyEight site,
Interactives is like a sidebar
and in some sense, The
Latest is like a sidebar.
Both of them are sidebars
to the main content here.
And when the screen shrinks down
they just go down to
the bottom of the page,
wherever that is.
Here they are.
Or with like a little bit
more typical of a sidebar,
here's Regent College's website
and I can make it
smaller, smaller, smaller.
This sidebar right here remains in place
until whatever this is,
maybe 800 pixels or something like that.
And then the 800 pixels
I'll have to scroll down
to the bottom of the
page and there it all is.
And this actually works out nicely, right?
Because if someone has read
through all of this page
and they're kinda wondering, what's next?
Where can I go to next?
What can I look at next?
Seeing this navigation right
here makes a lot of sense.
The other sidebar pattern
that's pretty useful
is to hide it in the top nav.
This is what we did in
the Rebalancr example
where something that was
a sidebar at wider widths
actually joins this kind of top nav
even if it's expandable at mobile sizes.
That being said, this sidebar
is only going to appear
when I'm at a size where I have this
hamburger button right here.
So as soon as I get big enough
where the hamburger button disappears,
in other words, 500 pixels,
I no longer have the option,
at least as currently designed
of having the sidebar
items in the top nav.
So where should I put them?
Should I try and do a
sidebar at 500 pixels?
That seems like very, very small
and kind of one of those things
that I'm gonna need to workout.
In order to figure out if it makes sense
to have a sidebar at this width,
I think the next best step
is to sort of do that
mobile first strategy.
I'm going to design the
screen all out at 320,
see what that looks like,
get that looking good,
and then start scaling it up.
And if a sidebar works here, awesome.
And if it doesn't, then
we'll do this kinda format
until a slightly wider width, no problem.
So what I'll do is press A,
grab my kinda small
screen size right here.
Put that there.
I'm gonna take this nav, paste it in,
and then do Command + Control + Up
and Command + Control + Left,
that's going to put this in
the top left hand corner.
And then I'm gonna get some of my
favorite little rulers in here.
16 pixels from the left,
16 pixels from the right,
and then one that's right in the middle.
So for 320, I think we're talking 160.
Perfect.
Now ignoring the sidebar
I can go and grab this header level one,
this H1 text if I wanna
use the HTML term for it
and put it in here.
And this leads us to talking about sizing
'cause right now this H1
it looks great for a desktop design.
But when I look at this mobile design,
like that's pretty big
and I'd have to pull it up on my phone
but I don't even think I need to do that.
I can tell that it is gonna
be kinda awkwardly big.
Fortunately, there is in the sizing lesson
a sizing UI cheat sheet.
And if I just go and
reference that real quick,
I can see here that it says
for H1, kinda the page title,
35 to 50 pixels is typical for desktop.
Whereas something more like 28
to 40 is typical for mobile.
So if I go back, my desktop size was 40,
so that's in that range,
but then I might wanna do something that
rather than being kind
of in the middle here,
it's actually more in
the middle for mobile.
So if I said, all right,
let's do something like 32 or whatever.
Maybe that would work just fine.
Another concern I would
have with this text
and this comes up all the
time in responsive design is
what's a realistic value here.
Like if someone says retirement portfolio,
should that spill over
onto two lines here?
And say, that's actually
a very common value.
If it's a very common value
and I wanna be space-conscious,
it really shouldn't.
And I'm not saying I would pick this size
just because of one value right here,
but the length of values that get inputted
whenever you're dealing
with user inputted text
is something that should
be taken into account
when you're picking
how to style that text.
In any case, if I pick the
size 28, that looks good
whether the title is retirement
or retirement portfolio.
And so, I'm just gonna run
with that for right now.
Now, when I look at this
second row right here,
To me this actually looks
like a perfect instance
where I could kind of use
the rows to columns pattern.
And I'll just do sort of two rows.
This would be the first row
and then this row would be the second row.
So I'd make like a mini
column out of this.
So I'm gonna grab these little stats,
put them right here.
Now, when I'm thinking about alignment,
I'm going to want to have the option
or one thing I'm gonna explore
is having the second stat
be aligned on the center line
and the first stat be aligned
in the left line here.
So these font sizes then
need to be small enough
such that the values
are not gonna collide.
So if I do something like 20 points,
that seems like it would work
and I'd even wanna pick
at least testing-wise,
we wanna test with an even
bigger portfolio number.
So like how many people would have
over 10 million on the site?
I'm not sure, right?
Like 88 seems extreme
but having a tens of
millions number right here
seems like this number
is either gonna need
to be quite a bit smaller
or we can push this over a little bit.
Of course, as soon as
we push this over a bit,
that's also implying that nothing else
on the bottom of the screen is going to
like use this center line as
a strong line of alignment.
If that was the case,
I think I would want this
one to be aligned here.
But since it's not, it
might just look fine
to like more like equalize the margins
such that this space is about
equivalent to this space
rather than have this overall APY
be aligned to the center line like this.
Now I'm gonna come retrieve these actions
and paste them in here.
And they actually fit
perfectly by coincidence,
which is really nice.
But one thing I wanna do is
for this mobile size here,
I'm actually going to make the
buttons a little bit taller.
Right now they have a 35 pixel tap target.
And let's go ahead and
add in a little bit more.
It's 43 and that already
looks pretty good.
Now the last thing I
wanna grab is these tabs
and these tabs are pretty easy to fit into
a phone screen's size here, fortunately.
It looks like just about the
only change I need to make,
here we go, is to bring
this in quite a bit.
And then maybe let's see,
these are 19 pixels tall
and there's 10 pixels of
padding on the bottom.
So if I assume there's 10 pixels
of padding on the top too,
then that's a tap target
size of about 44 points.
So that's actually good.
And then kinda put these
maybe about right here
and yeah, that doesn't look too bad.
Now, from this point,
the last big thing that
I need to make responsive
is this table
and that's complicated enough
that we're gonna break it
out into its own subject
with its own patterns.
But right now, I just
wanna use this excuse
to talk about some other
kind of text patterns
that you might want to be aware of
when doing responsive design.
The first pattern I wanna talk about
is just this underlying principle
that applies across all devices.
Whether you're talking about
reading texts on the phone
or reading texts on a TV
that's across the room,
or even reading text on
a book or on a billboard
that's across the highway.
Font sizes are all ultimately
about angular sizes.
And this is something
I linked to this below
but this is an article I wrote.
And one of the important ideas here
is that whatever device
you're viewing your text on,
if you were to draw say
a line from your eye
to the bottom of the text, the baseline,
and the line from your eye
to the top of the text,
the cap height or in
this case the X height,
the angle between those two
lines should always be the same.
That means no matter what
device you're looking at
and how far away it is,
there's sort of this trade-off here,
the farther away the device is,
the bigger the letters are gonna get.
And so, there's all this complicated math
that has to do with pixel density.
And like ultimately this doesn't lead to
an easy rule for what
size in terms of pixels
your text should be.
But if you follow the sizing cheat sheet
that's gonna be no problem.
And ultimately this pattern
is just making the point that
for instance, if you're
reading a paragraph of text,
that should be as easy
to do on a billboard
as it should be on a book.
It should be as easy to
do on a, say a smart TV
as it is on your mobile phone.
Because the text should
always sort of take up
the same amount of space
in your field of vision.
If that's paragraphs of
text, it's gonna be smaller
and if that's something
like a big headline,
that's gonna be larger.
But across devices, across distances,
you always wanna make
sure that your text is
say as legible as just holding a book
at a normal book holding
distance and just reading it.
Another text pattern that's
very important to keep in mind
for responsive design
is that the ideal line length of text
is measured in characters,
it's not measured in
pixels or anything else
and it's 50 to 75 characters.
We've talked about how
this is a good balance
between not having to
skip lines that often
but also being able to track very easily
from the end of one line to
the beginning of the next.
And one example that I
think does this pretty well
is Trent Walton's site.
And if you look at his site,
like I can kinda go in here.
And actually if I do inspect
and bring up the dev tools,
another fun thing that I can do
is add some text to the site.
For instance, I like to
add those three alphabets.
Three alphabets means that
if the line length matches
somewhere between the
beginning of the third alphabet
and the end of the third alphabet,
I'm in that 50 to 75 character range.
And you can see that even
as the screen size changes,
his font size changes we
already saw it changed twice.
Three times.
Four times.
And it's really only, once I
get down to whatever this is,
600 pixels or so
where I'm not gonna continue
shrinking the font size
and then the line length
becomes a little bit smaller.
It's everything above
that 600 pixels or so
follows that guideline of having
50 to 75 characters per line.
And that means a number of break points
where the font just gets
excessively bigger and bigger
because if it maintained
a very small size,
like the small column of
text would be totally lost
in this huge sea of tan.
Now we've already talked
about line length plenty
so I'm not gonna go into that anymore.
The next pattern that I
think is really worth knowing
is that you always have the availability
to remove extra words
or to add abbreviations
or to do like small little detail work
to make things fit on smaller pages.
So for instance on this MDCalc
design that I worked on,
here we've got different
tabs that I can choose.
Most Popular, Recents, Favorites,
My Specialty, All, and Newest.
When I shrink this down,
just go ahead and shrink
it all the way down.
You'll see that something
like My Specialty
becomes Specialty
and Most Popular here
becomes just Popular here.
And this Newest tab that I can see on
kinda this tablet width
totally disappears.
There is no Newest tab when I'm on mobile.
This is like little detail work
but it really does help to
try and make the experience
seem as reasonable as possible
even on the smallest screen widths.
All right.
And now, after talking about
some of those text patterns,
it comes time for us to talk about
kind of the doozy of responsive design.
This is the thing that I most commonly
receive questions about in
the world responsive design,
how do I do responsive tables?
And I'm gonna show you a
couple of patterns for this
but ultimately the solution
that we're going to take in this app
is something that's a
little bit more custom
and a little bit more based on
specifically how this data works.
So it's not really just a
one size fits all pattern
for how we're going to do this.
The first table pattern
that I wanna talk about
is called row-to-mini-table
or I suppose you could call
it all sorts of things.
But the idea is when I have,
let's say just a table here.
if I look got James, Matman, The, Tick,
Jokey, Smurf, et cetera,
all with job titles and other data
that's put into this table.
When I get down to a width where
it no longer makes sense
to display this as a table,
what's going to happen
is each row of the table
is going to become its own
mini table with two columns.
It's gonna become its own
set of key value pairs
or label value pairs.
So, first name that was a
column title at a wider width
and now it's actually
just a label for James.
Last name was a column title here
and now it's just a label for Matman.
And the same thing when I go
down to like the second row
of values right here, I
have those labels reprinted.
So in some sense this is really redundant
because the first name
label gets reprinted
every single time I have what was a row
in the lighter table.
But this also displays all the data
in a way that makes a
lot of sense for a small
kinda narrow screen.
So that's the row-to-mini-table pattern.
Another pattern that might
just be kind of obvious
is you can just always remove
the least important rows, right?
This is like our general
pattern of removing stuff.
Here's another demo,
it's actually hard to find
responsive tables in the wild
despite being asked about it all the time.
Here's another demo
where as I shrink down,
there are just a bunch of columns
that get downright removed.
Like I can't scroll to see them
although that would be
a possibility, right?
I can always just say,
oh, this table is horizontally scrollable.
But nope, sometimes it's easier
just to completely remove
some of those columns
that aren't as important
and get something that is
a little bit more sensible
for a smaller screen.
And if you haven't
watched the Tables lesson,
that has a great example
where I go through
a lot of hassle to try and
make a table more narrow.
Not necessarily so it
fits on a mobile device,
but I talk about every
other strategy in the book
including removing the
least important rows
for when it comes to
making a table smaller.
Another very interesting
pattern that you can use
for mobile tables is to flip the axis
and allow horizontal scrolling.
So this only works for a
specific subset of tables.
This works for tables that are much longer
than they are tall.
So in this case, I've got a
lot of different columns here
but not all that many rows
or at least when I look at the
ultimate display of the table,
it just feels kinda long.
What I'm gonna have happen
though is these values,
these labels, Numbers, Names,
Values, Dates, Cash Money,
Messages, and Buttons,
they're originally all across the top.
But when I shrink the table on down,
then they're across the
side, not across the top.
Numbers, Names, Values, Dates,
Cash Money, Messages, and Buttons.
And at this point I
can't see all the values
but because horizontal
scrolling is enabled,
I can scroll across.
The labels are still fixed
so it's very easy to see
what each piece of data,
what it belongs to here
or what it's labeled by.
But between these two changes,
flipping the axis and then
allowing horizontal scrolling,
it actually makes for a
much more decent experience.
Again, this is one that you're gonna want
to think about doing
especially if you have a very long table.
The taller the table is on desktop
or on the original format,
the more horizontal scrolling
is gonna be involved.
And ultimately there's kind of a limit
to where that is useful and fun on mobile.
And the final table pattern
that I wanna talk about
and this is gonna be the
one that we actually use
in our own project here is to
reformat the table as a list.
And this is something that when we do it,
we're kind of gonna do it in a custom way.
It's not like there's
just a couple of styles
you can apply or kind of an
algorithm that you can run
to take any table and
change it into a list.
Instead, what we're gonna
do is we're gonna say,
look on mobile devices it's
very common to have lists.
Right, there's lists, you
might have in an email inbox.
It's just a list of emails.
And in that list you can have,
for instance, primary
data, secondary data.
Some texts might be kind of left-align,
some texts might be right-aligned.
All of this stuff is very
common to see on mobile devices.
What we're gonna try and do is format
the data in this table
such that each row of this
table fits into a row of a list.
So I'm gonna start just by making this
a little bit bigger.
And one common thing with mobile lists
is for them to have a slightly
darker background color.
And I actually like this.
It just makes it,
it's like one way to
kinda set apart the list
from the other content on the page.
I'm gonna lock it cause I don't expect
to change sizes too often.
And then I'm gonna start by grabbing
what I feel like is the most primary
kinda piece of information,
almost like the label for the row here.
The symbol is what comes first
but I myself couldn't
identify these symbols.
I'm not sure how many people can
and I actually think
this human readable name
would work better for something like this.
So actually I'll grab all of these here
and I'll come paste them in.
I'm gonna go with the
same line of alignment
that everything else has.
And then I'm going to make
sure that the line height
plus the paragraph spacing
or wait, not paragraph spacing.
It's actually the distance
between the different text boxes
'cause these are all different text boxes.
I'm gonna make sure this
adds up to at least 44.
So I think this needs to be
24 if this is 20 right here.
But I know because there's so much data
that I'm gonna fit in here
that I'm actually gonna
have two lines of texts.
Like below the name of the asset here,
I'm probably gonna try
and put the symbol in
in kind of a primary,
secondary text pattern.
If I do that, then I want the row height
to be taller than 44 in all likelihood.
So if I just like skip
this up to 30 pixels,
now 30 plus 20 that's 50,
like I'll try something like
that and see how that looks.
So let's press Enter.
I'm gonna shift things
down just a little bit here
and there we go, that might be good.
Now I'm gonna take these
and do the same thing.
I'm gonna paste them in.
I'm gonna say that's 30, that's 20.
And then, oops, I guess
I need to set that.
And then I'm gonna make
this two font sizes smaller
and give it something
like an opacity of 70%.
That is the primary secondary text pattern
that you probably remember
from the typography unit.
And I'll just put this little
ticker symbol or whatever
immediately below the human readable name.
And already, this is starting to appear
a little bit more like kind
of a standard mobile list
that we know and are used to.
Now at this point, it's
clear to me that like,
we're going to fit in
about two more pieces of
information max, right?
Like most mobile lists will have
maybe one thing on the
right-hand side here.
And what I need to do is figure out
what that one thing is
that would make sense.
And this is why there's no
like one size fits all approach
for reformatting a table as a list
'cause it comes down to like
do users wanna see the current price
of whatever index fund this is?
Or do they wanna see the quantity
that they have in their own portfolio?
Do they wanna see the value
that that represents in the portfolio?
In my uninformed opinion my
guess is probably the value,
it's not the cost basis.
And maybe the target
percentage would be useful
but the current percentage
that this represents
seems like the most reasonable thing.
So if I'm gonna put in
two more values here,
I'm gonna take the value and
the portfolio percentage.
I'm gonna do a primary, secondary pattern
on the right-hand side.
So let's just look at that real quick.
All right, so this is a good start.
You notice I did a couple things.
First of all, when the price,
when I noticed that the price
was sort of the longer of the two values,
I thought, you know what,
I'll actually have that
be the secondary value
so that it's less likely
to run into the text.
Plus I think kind of,
if this app is all about
keeping your portfolio
rebalanced like, or balanced.
It's called Rebalancr
so presumably it's like doing
that somewhat automatically.
Then knowing the percent here
is actually like a very reasonable value
to be the primary data here.
But one thing I might wanna do is say,
I need to have a cap on say
how long this text can be, right?
Like I should not have these
pieces of text colliding.
And so, maybe there's gonna be
20 pixels of space between them,
maybe it's more, maybe it's less.
I don't really know.
This is something that
you could play around with
once it was actually coded up
and see like what feels
like a good value here.
But something like that
might make more sense.
Now, one of the intentions
of doing a table like this,
now one of my intentions
in doing a table like this
is not that the other data
just completely disappears,
it's that the other data in the table,
and then the actions associated
with these different funds here
would be available by
tapping anywhere on this row.
Like you could tap on this row
and then whatever other things
you would need to have happen
would like be available
in say a little pop-up
or something like that.
But for the data that's most important
that will just be
displayed on this list item
the entire time.
And so there we go.
I've sort of finished
this up just by doing
some pretty normal list styling.
I've got a slightly darker
border at the very top
and the very bottom.
Maybe I'll lighten those just
a bit like 15% or something.
And then lighter ones throughout,
these are 10% opacity black.
So at this point, if we have
something that looks good
and I think we do,
I've looked at this on a real device,
then I want to kind of
return to the question of
what are we gonna do about a sidebar
as soon as we have this
little menu disappearing?
So when the hamburger menu disappears,
the sidebar needs to be
present 100% of the time
unless I did some other thing
like put the sidebar
in the top or whatever.
But I just don't think
that's gonna work out great
in this particular instance.
So I'm going to make another design
at something like 500 pixels
and oh, interesting, none of that text
actually got registered
as being part here.
So I'll take my 500
pixel nav, put it here.
This stuff all looks pretty good.
I guess what I could experiment
with is just grouping this
and seeing if it goes all the way
to the right-hand side here,
how much room I have for
something like a sidebar.
So if I go grab my sidebar right here,
right now it's 143 pixels wide.
Oh, look at that.
It's actually like, it
feels like plenty of room.
Like what's the minimum
distance I need here?
These two are selectable.
Settings, Tax Documents
would also be selectable.
But at no point is this blue rectangle
going to actually run in
with any of this stuff.
So this may actually be fine as is
or I could do something like
put eight pixels of space
just for the heck of it.
And then I can expand all of
these to take up the space
that's allotted to them
and finally have that right there.
Now at this point, I
wanna kinda keep it up.
I wanna keep making
wider and wider versions
at each version being kinda
sort of as natural as possible
with how things would appear.
So, as this gets wider and wider,
I'm gonna ask myself what
is sort of the minimum width
at which this just becomes too awkward
and almost sort of demands to
be something else entirely?
Like it just needs to be reformatted again
with a different break point.
And so, especially if I have this content
sort of floating right here,
I still feel like this can
get a little bit wider.
And so, right now we're at 624
but maybe it's something
like maybe 800 pixels
is where we reached the
point where we can actually
just have a completely
different display of information
and we no longer need this
like mobile style display
of the content right here.
So there we go, I made
another version of this table
where it's sort of intermediate,
it's not quite the list view.
It does some things to
sort of shorten the table
like this symbol here has
written a secondary text
below the name.
And then I do things like
drop the cost basis column
which doesn't seem super, super useful.
But it helps this table
feel like something that is
the most logical view
and the most logical design and layout
for something like 800 pixels wide.
And then I think this would work until,
I mean, this would be the next step here,
a certain width at which I
could fit this whole table.
And also one of the things
that's interesting about
sort of doing this mobile first approach
is another thing I did was I
changed the word percentage
into just the percent sign
and that seems way more logical
for something like this.
So when I'm working mobile first,
a lot of times I'm gonna find these ways
of making things more
efficient or better displays.
I'm gonna find ways to do
things better at larger sizes
just by working on smaller sizes
and this is like one of many examples.
Now I wanna wrap this example up.
I think you really get the idea
for how this sort of thing works.
My next steps would be
to go and make sure that
say the absolute largest
size of this format
still looks pretty good.
And then then the minimum size
of the next one looks good
and that carries through all the way
to the largest size of this one and so on.
So that each break point
across all of its width
it's gonna look really good
and just have such a stunning layout
that it seems like this app was designed
to be viewed at that size.
From there, I'm just gonna like
double check for consistency
and a totally logical
pattern across sizes.
So there's all sorts of little
things that change here.
Like I know we talked
about the margins here,
this is 48 on one side
and right now it's 44 on the other side.
So I'd wanna make sure
I'm very clear about
what does that mean?
Should this actually be 46
and it's centered between the sidebar
and the right-hand side,
or is this gonna be at this break point,
is this just gonna be 44
pixels from the sidebar
and it's locked there
even as 10 more pixels
get added onto the screen?
Just wanna be very consistent
and clear on exactly what
all those little effects are.
And once I've reached that point,
then I want to kind of write down
the overall scheme for what happens
across all different screen sizes,
as well as the schemes for different like
little states that might
be unique to mobile
and things like that.
And I wanna start involving the developer.
I wanna start having a conversation
with whoever's gonna be coding this up
and just making sure they're
clear on all these things
and that they're able to do all of it.
That it all seems sort of logical
and kind of go from there.
And if you're interested
in more along those veins
do watch the Developer Handoff video.
Now we've already talked
about all the patterns
that went into this Rebalancr project
but I want to actually
finish things up here
by going over a few other patterns
that weren't necessary
for this little project
but are still things that
you're gonna come across.
So really quickly, I
wanna go into two patterns
for grids and lists.
One thing that's very
important to be aware of
when you're working with a
grid is that you can have
a flexible width an item in that grid
but you can also have a flexible
number of items per row.
So if I go to something like Pinterest,
at the 1440 width that I'm at right now,
I've got five items across.
As the screen size shrinks though,
in this case, they are not going to adjust
the size of the item,
they're just going to adjust
the number of items per row.
So it goes from five to four to three.
And then when we get
down to a mobile size,
I've got two right here.
An alternative might be something like
what Row 7 Seeds does
where if I go down to their
different seeds that they sell,
right now it's three across
and it continues to be three across
with the only difference
being these images shrink.
And then at some break point,
maybe around a thousand I've got two
and the images continue to shrink.
And then I snapped down to one
And so, by adjusting both the image size
or like the size of this grid item,
as well as how many grid
items appear per row,
I can have like pretty fine grain control
and make sure I'm doing something
that's like an absolutely ideal display
for every given size.
Another good list pattern to know about
is collapsible list items.
So if we're oftentimes
taking things that are rows
and making them into columns,
that can lead to a lot of vertical content
that may be a little bit
more than what you want.
So one thing that Starbucks
does here is in their footer,
if they were to just list out all of these
in a single column,
like take this row of
columns and make it into
a column of columns,
that would take up an
enormous amount of space.
And so what they do is even
though this is the footer,
they know that not everyone
wants to see all of these links.
And so by default, they've
minimized each of them
into just the title of
that sort of sub list.
And so this is a great
pattern to know about
being able to minimize a
column and collapse a list
into something that's a little
bit more scrolling-friendly.
Photography and imagery patterns
are also super important
for responsive design.
Probably the most important ones
that we didn't actually cover
in the live example that we did
but I wanna cover them now really quickly.
So one pattern that comes up quite a bit
is the media object pattern.
It's a bit of a strange name
but it just refers to any time
you have both text and image,
but oftentimes specifically
laid out horizontally.
So here I have an image
on the left-hand side
and some texts that goes along with it
on the right hand side.
It may actually seem kind of strange
that on a very small screen width,
I have the text in the image side by side.
Whereas on a larger screen width,
I have the text and the
image one above the other.
But this can work out really nicely
because if you make a single
image full width on mobile,
oftentimes it can turn
out to be really tall.
And especially when my screen
height isn't that tall,
like this watch and learn is ultimately
taking up more screen real estate
and causing me to do more scrolling
than almost any other
article on the entire page,
and all the other articles
are the most important part.
So there's sort of this thing where
a lot of times you may actually
want the image to be smaller
when you're on a smaller screen size
so that it doesn't require
so much obnoxious scrolling.
And this media object, this idea of having
some piece of media on the left
and some text on the right
is a good way to do it.
But anytime you have that
pattern where you have
say text and image side by side,
you should also remember
that you have the ability
to flip it to be vertical as well.
And if you're flexible with that,
you've got say, quite a lot of options
for different layouts
across screen widths.
So the media object is one powerful
imagery pattern to be aware of
but another one with
perhaps even a stranger name
is art direction.
And I realize art
direction is in some ways
kind of a subfield of design
but it's also just become
I guess the industry term
for the idea of using
slightly different images
at different screen sizes.
So the one example we've
seen of this already
is Contents Magazine and the fact that
like they are very likely
loading up different image files.
I guess I can't really tell for sure
but it seems like it's
different image files
at different screen sizes
such that they're
conveying the overall idea
of this sort of smattering
of colorful books
laid out tastefully around the screen
but they're not taking
just the easy route of like
having one image that kind of scales,
or just runs off the side of the screen
when it gets smaller.
Instead they're looking
at every screen size
as if it's the only
screen size and saying,
how would we put the
smattering of books right now?
And then trying to transition
fluidly between all of them.
So, like I said, this has earned
the somewhat strange name of art direction
in the world of responsive images.
One other example that I think
is just incredibly clever
is there is this Made in
Germany Design magazine
and one thing that they
do with their header image
apart from having this nice
layering effect right here
is when I get down to
a smaller screen size,
I just have the issue
number and that's it.
I don't even have any other title.
And I only start to see this
Dmig, Design Made in Germany
when there's much more room for it.
So they're sort of using this idea of
considering the screen
as if that screen size
is the only screen size
you're designing for it
and saying, what would the
solution look like here?
And when that's mobile, it
might look quite a bit different
and a little bit more
minimalistic in some sense
than when that's a full
width desktop version.
One other pattern that's
important to know about
when you're talking about mobile imagery
is having labels be above the images.
This is a very simple idea
but there's something kinda powerful here.
So the New York Times actually
does a really good job with this pattern.
If I look at sort of the
main story of the day,
I've got some text and
these images side by side.
When I'm on a large screen,
my eye can really easily see
that this text is
associated with these images
and I can bounce back and
forth between them no problem.
But when I'm on a small screen,
oftentimes like I said,
that image can take up
quite a bit of screen height.
And if this image, I mean,
if it gets any taller,
then if the text that goes with the image
is below the image,
it can be really difficult to
kind of scroll through the entire image
and then see the text
that gives you context.
And then maybe you have to
scroll back up to the image
to take a glance at it.
By putting the contextual
text above the image,
it just makes it easier
to take in some of this.
And I would say they
could even do something
like put the image between the headline
and these little bullet points right here.
But whatever, that's extra credit.
So anyhow, the New York
Times does a good job
on the mobile version.
As I scroll, I always get a headline
and a little bit of context
before I then see that richer image
that adds a little bit more.
But I never had the effect
of looking at an image,
wondering what it's about,
and then finding out
once I've scrolled down
400 pixels past it.
The final set of patterns
that I wanna cover
is form patterns
and these are all gonna be
fairly straightforward things
based on everything that
we've talked about so far.
So the first one is side
labels to top labels.
When you have a wide screen,
oftentimes if you want a form to take up
a little bit more horizontal width
and kinda own that space,
it's very reasonable to put labels
on the left-hand side of the form fields
that they relate to.
However, when the screen size shrinks,
you don't always have that luxury
and so at some point
it becomes very natural
to have the form label go
on top of each of the fields
that it refers to.
That's it, that's the pattern.
Another pattern that makes a lot of sense
for dealing with forms
across different screen sizes
is shrinking a multi-column
form to a single column forum.
So of course, this is the same thing
as the general rows to columns pattern
that we've talked about again and again
but here if I have this form that has
one, two, three different
columns of fields
that need to be dealt with,
if I shrink the screen size
Harvest very intelligently puts them all
into a single column that I can deal with.
And what's more, has a nice little thing
telling me to use their mobile app
instead of trying to struggle
through their mobile website,
so that's just gonna be
an even better experience.
That's a very cool little
responsive design detail.
And the final form pattern
that I wanna mention
is I call it sub-element resizing
but this is just the
resizing that you need to do
on a couple different things
that are very commonly in forms.
For instance, one of them is buttons.
We talked about how buttons should be
let's say at least 44 by 44 points.
But another one that you
don't hear of as often
is text boxes.
If on an iPhone, you click into a text box
that has less than size 16 text,
it's actually gonna do this forced zoom
and it's gonna zoom in.
And that can be kinda jarring
and sort of mess with your design.
And the idea here is like very sensible,
Apple just wants people
to have a decent font size
to deal with if they're
gonna be typing out data.
But the forced zoom can
be a little bit awkward
and so I would just recommend
that whatever project you're working on,
if you have forms,
just make the font size
within those text fields
16 point or bigger.
And here, if I look right here,
I am guilty as charged 'cause
I forgot to do that of course.
Find it eventually when I
tested on an actual iPhone
but it's better just to be able
to do this stuff right away.
So search funds, research,
and here's another example
of mobile first making sense.
If I just put et cetera here,
that actually works better
and it's nice and short too.
So I can use et cetera for mobile, tablet,
and across all the different designs.
All right, folks.
And that wraps it up
for Responsive Design.
So I know that was an
absolute doozy of a video.
I apologize for the length
but this truly is an important skill
in transferring pretty pictures in Figma
into the real world of actually
shipping a designed website
to millions of people.
Beyond all the content
that we've talked about,
take a look at some of the
links and resources below.
They're gonna be very handy
for referencing down the road,
but also take a look at
the homework assignment.
You're gonna be doing something
somewhat similar to the
example that we talked about.
And as always, if you have any questions,
let me know in the student community.
And we'll see in the next video.